# DAVID ALBRECHT (HE/HIM)

https://da-lbrecht.github.io im/www.linkedin.com/in/david-albrecht-2b4479120

#### **SUMMARY**

I am a behavioral economist and internationally experienced consultant interested in generating and applying insights on trans-contextual questions related to economics and decision-making. In my research, I explore topics such as collective intelligence and economic preferences using experiments, surveys, empirical analysis, structural estimations, Bayesian statistics, and machine learning.

#### CURRENT POSITION

#### PhD Candidate in Human Decisions and Policy Design

Sep 2019 - expected Feb 2024

Maastricht University, The Netherlands

Supervisors: Alexander Brüggen, Martin Strobel, and Thomas Meissner

#### RESEARCH PAPERS

Job Market Paper: Mitigating manipulation in committees: Just let them talk! - link

• I analyze how the format of interaction and threats of manipulation influence the accuracy and trustworthiness of judgments derived in small groups such as expert committees or project teams.

**Debt Aversion: Theory and Measurement** (with Thomas Meissner) - *link* 

• We propose a formal model incorporating debt aversion as a genuine domain of preferences and use a novel experiment to jointly estimate debt aversion with preferences over time, risk, and losses.

The Debt Aversion Survey Module: An experimentally validated tool to measure individual debt aversion (with Thomas Meissner) - link

• We develop an experimentally validated, short and easy-to-use survey module for measuring individual preferences towards saving and borrowing, as if elicited through an incentivized experiment.

#### ONGOING RESEARCH

#### Debt aversion among German households

(with Thomas Meissner and Ciril Bosch-Rosa)

• We investigate the relation of individual debt attitudes to other socio-economic characteristics and its predictive power for real-world behavior based on a German representative sample.

#### REFERENCES

Martin Strobel (m.strobel (at) maastrichtuniversity.nl)

Maastricht University, Microeconomics & Public Economics

Alexander Brüggen (a.bruggen (at) maastrichtuniversity.nl)

Maastricht University, Accounting & Information Management

Thomas Meissner (t.meissner (at) maastrichtuniversity.nl)

Maastricht University, Microeconomics & Public Economics

Karsten Mau (k.mau (at) maastrichtuniversity.nl)

Maastricht University, Macro, International & Labour Economics

#### ACADEMIC VISITS

#### Visiting Graduate Student

Oct 2023

Technische Universität Berlin, Germany - Host Prof. Dr. Frank Heinemann

# Visiting Graduate Student

Sep 2022 - Jan 2023

University of California, San Diego - Rady School of Management, USA - Host Uri Gneezy

#### AWARDS

#### Maastricht University - GSBE International Travel Grant (€3000)

2022

• Research visit - Rady School of Management at UC San Diego

# Maastricht University - GSBE Grant for Primary Data Collection (€7200)

2021

• Hidden Agendas in Small Group Judgment Aggregation

#### SEMINAR ORGANIZATION

# Interdisciplinary Seminar of Behavioral Sciences - Theory and Empirics

Since 2022

- link to seminar webpage

#### TEACHING AND TEACHING INNOVATION

# Maastricht University

Since 2019

- Economics and Business, History of Economic Thought, Public Economics, Data Workshops (Python), Economy Game, Economy Game for MBA, Growth & Institutions
- Economy Game 2.0: Develop a double auction market tool in oTree (Python, JavaScript, and HTML) to facilitate experience-based education on markets and their economic implications.

# ACADEMIC PRESENTATIONS

UM Behavioral Insights Center Research Retreat

2023

ESA Job Market Seminar Series

ESA Europe Meeting Exeter

EEA ESEM Meeting Barcelona

Maastricht Behavioral Economics Symposium

IAREP SABE Annual Meeting Nice

ESA North America Meeting Santa Barbara

2022

UC San Diego Theoretical & Behavioral Economics Seminar

UC San Diego Graduate Student Research Seminar

Maastricht University Interdisciplinary Seminar of Behavioral Sciences – Theory and Empirics

Maastricht University BEElab meeting

ESA Global Conference (online)

2021

EADM Subjective Probability, Utility and Decision Making Conference (online)

Maastricht Behavioral Economics Symposium

Lyon-Maastricht Behavioral Workshop (online)

Maastricht University MU-CEN Seminar

Maastricht University Behavioral and Experimental Economics Reading Group

2020

#### **EDUCATION**

# M.Sc. in Economics and Management Science (MEMS) Humboldt University, Berlin, Germany Thesis: Probability Perception in Decision Making under Risk Study visit: Tel Aviv University, Israel 2016 B.A. in Economics and Sociology Georg August University, Göttingen, Germany Study visit: University of Groningen, The Netherlands 2017 2017 2017 2017 2018 2018 2019 2019 2019 2019 2019 2019

#### PREVIOUS POSITIONS

# Senior Consultant (earlier Consultant)

2017 - 2019

BwConsulting GmbH, Berlin, Germany

- Solved managerial and economic challenges of the German Ministry of Defence by applying good project and change management practices to a major organizational area of ~35 000 employees.
- Implemented a goal-oriented system of organizational development and program management.
- Lead-authored papers on behavioral insights for strategic decisions and robotic process automation.

# Various internships in Economic and Management Consulting

2014 - 2017

FehrAdvice & Partners AG (Zurich - CHE), Deutsche Bahn Management Consulting (Berlin - GER), NERA Economic Consulting (Berlin - GER), IGEP Foundation (Gurgaon - IND)

# INVOLVEMENT

# **Foodsaver**

Foodsharing Maastricht, Netherlands

2020 - 2022

• Fight food waste by collecting and redistributing expired, edible food from vendors and retailers.

#### SKILLS AND INTERESTS

Technical: MS Office, LaTex, R, Python, oTree, STATA, Mathematica, zTree, ORSEE

Soft Skills: Project Leadership, Facilitation, PBL-Teaching

Fields of Interest: Behavioral Science, Data Analysis, Effective Altruism, Degrowth, Bicycles and

Cycling, Espresso, Cuisine and Food Production, Tailoring, Urban Gardening, and many more

Languages: German, English, Dutch, Italian, French